Imagine being unable to say, "I am hungry," "I am in pain,"
تخيل أن لاتكون قادراً على قول ، "أنا جائع ،" أنا أتألم "
"thank you," or "I love you."
"شكراً" أو "أحبك."
Being trapped inside your body,
أن تكون عالقاً في داخل جسدك،
a body that doesn't respond to commands.
في جسد لايجيب للأوامر.
Surrounded by people,
محاط بالناس،
yet utterly alone.
لكنك وحيد تماماً.
Wishing you could reach out,
تتمنى لو تستطيع أن تتواصل
to connect, to comfort, to participate.
أن تتصل أن تواسي أن تشارك
For 13 long years, that was my reality.
لقرابة ال 13 عام ، كان هذا واقعي
Most of us never think twice about talking, about communicating.
معظمنا لايفكر مرتين عن التحدث ، عن التواصل
I've thought a lot about it.
لقد فكرت كثيراً في هذا
I've had a lot of time to think.
كان لدي الكثير من الوقت للتفكير
For the first 12 years of my life,
في أول 12 عام من حياتي
I was a normal, happy, healthy little boy.
كنت طفل طبيعي سعيد وصحيح
Then everything changed.
بعد ذلك تغير كل شي
I contracted a brain infection.
أصبت بعدوى في الدماغ
The doctors weren't sure what it was,
لم يكن الاطباء متأكدين عن ماهيته
but they treated me the best they could.
لكنهم عالجوني بأفضل مالديهم
However, I progressively got worse.
مع ذلك، زاد الأمر سوءاً
Eventually, I lost my ability to control my movements,
بنهاية الأمر ، خسرت القدرة على التحكم في حركاتي
make eye contact,
أن أتواصل بعيني
and finally, my ability to speak.
وأخيراً ، قدرتي على الكلام.
While in hospital,
حين كنت في المستشفى ،
I desperately wanted to go home.
أردت بشدة أن أعود للمنزل.
I said to my mother, "When home?"
قلت لوالدتي ، "متى المنزل ؟"
Those were the last words I ever spoke with my own voice.
كانت هذه آخر الكلمات التي قلتها بصوتي.
I would eventually fail every test for mental awareness.
ثم أنتهى الأمر بي أخفق في كل أختبار للوعي العقلي.
My parents were told I was as good as not there.
أخبروا والديّ بأنني بخير كما لو أنني لست موجوداً
A vegetable, having the intelligence of a three-month-old baby.
نبات، قدرتي العقلية كما طفل في عمر الثلاثة أشهر
They were told to take me home and try to keep me comfortable
أخبروا والديّ أن ياخذوني للمنزل ويحاولوا الاعتناء بي
until I died.
حتى أموت
My parents, in fact my entire family's lives,
والديّ، في الواقع حياة كل أفراد عائلتي
became consumed by taking care of me the best they knew how.
أصبحت مستهلكة برعايتي بأفضل مالديهم
Their friends drifted away.
أصدقائهم أبتعدوا عنهم
One year turned to two,
السنة أصبحت سنتين
two turned to three.
السنتين أصبحت ثلاثة
It seemed like the person I once was began to disappear.
بدأ وكانما الشخص الذي كنت عليه بدأ يختفي
The Lego blocks and electronic circuits I'd loved as a boy were put away.
مكعبات ليغو والدوائر الألكترونية التي أحببت كفتى قد وضعت جانباً.
I had been moved out of my bedroom into another more practical one.
تم نقلي من غرفتي الى أخرى أكثر عمليه
I had become a ghost,
أصبحت شبح
a faded memory of a boy people once knew and loved.
ذكرى متلاشيه لفتى قد أحبه وعرفه الناس
Meanwhile, my mind began knitting itself back together.
وفي الوقت نفسه، بدأ عقلي يحيك نفسه إلى ماكان عليه من جديد
Gradually, my awareness started to return.
تدريجياً ، بدأ وعيي للعودة.
But no one realized that I had come back to life.
لكن لم يلاحظ أحد أنني قد عدت للحياة مجدداً
I was aware of everything,
كنت على علم بكل شيء،
just like any normal person.
تماماً كأي شخص طبيعي
I could see and understand everything,
أستطيع أن أرى وأفهم كل شيء
but I couldn't find a way to let anybody know.
لكن لم أستطع أن أجد طريقة لأخبار أي أحد
My personality was entombed within a seemingly silent body,
شخصيتي كانت مدفونه داخل مايبدو الجسد الصامت ،
a vibrant mind hidden in plain sight within a chrysalis.
عقل نابض بالحياة مخبأ داخل شرنقة على مرأى من الجميع.
The stark reality hit me that I was going to spend
صٌدمت بالحقيقة القاسية بأنني سأقضي
the rest of my life locked inside myself,
بقية حياتي عالقاُ داخل نفسي .
totally alone.
وحيد تماماً.
I was trapped with only my thoughts for company.
كنت محاصراً فقط مع أفكاري ترافقني.
I would never be rescued.
لن ينقذني أحد.
No one would ever show me tenderness.
لن يحن علي أحد ابداً.
I would never talk to a friend.
لن أتحدث إلى صديق أبداً.
No one would ever love me.
لن يحبني أحد.
I had no dreams, no hope, nothing to look forward to.
لا أحلام لدي ، لاأمنيات ، لاشيء أتطلع إليه.
Well, nothing pleasant.
حسناً ، لاشيء ممتع.
I lived in fear,
عشت في خوف ،
and, to put it bluntly,
سأقولها بصراحة
was waiting for death to finally release me,
كنت بأنتظار الموت أخيراً ليحررني،
expecting to die all alone in a care home.
متوقعاً أن أموت وحيداً في أحدى دور الرعاية.
I don't know if it's truly possible to express in words
لاأعلم أن كان ممكناً حقاً أن أعبر في كلمات
what it's like not to be able to communicate.
ماذا يعني حقاً أن تكون عاجزاً عن التواصل.
Your personality appears to vanish into a heavy fog
شخصيتك تبدأ تتلاشى في الضباب الكثيف
and all of your emotions and desires are constricted, stifled and muted within you.
وجميع عواطفك ورغباتك محاصره ، مكبوتة ، صامتة في داخلك.
For me, the worst was the feeling of utter powerlessness.
بالنسبة لي ، الأسوء كان الشعور بالعجز التام ،
I simply existed.
ببساطة ، أنا فقط موجود.
It's a very dark place to find yourself
أنه مكان مظلم أن تجد نفسك فيه
because in a sense, you have vanished.
لأنه بمعنى ما ، لقد تلاشيت.
Other people controlled every aspect of my life.
أشخاص آخرين تحكموا بكل جانب من جوانب حياتي
They decided what I ate and when.
يقرروا ماذا أكل ومتى ،
Whether I was laid on my side or strapped into my wheelchair.
سواء أيجب إلقائي على جانبي أو مقيد في الكرسي المتحرك
I often spent my days positioned in front of the TV
قضيت أغلب أيامي (مُثبتاً) أمام التلفاز
watching Barney reruns.
مشاهداً بارني (ويعاد كل مره)
I think because Barney is so happy and jolly,
أعتقد لأن بارني كان سعيداً ومرحاً،
and I absolutely wasn't,
وأنا بكل تأكيد لم أكن ،
it made it so much worse.
جعل الأمر أكثر سوءاً .
I was completely powerless to change anything in my life
كنت عاجزاً تماماً أن أغير اي شيء في حياتي
or people's perceptions of me.
أو تصورات الناس لي .
I was a silent, invisible observer of how people behaved
كنت صامتاً، مراقب غير مرئي لكيف يتصرف الآخرين
when they thought no one was watching.
بينما كانوا يعتقدوا أن لا أحد يراهم.
Unfortunately, I wasn't only an observer.
للأسف ، لم أكن فقط مراقباً
With no way to communicate, I became the perfect victim:
بدون طريقة للتواصل لكن أصبحت أيضاً الضحية المثالية ،
a defenseless object, seemingly devoid of feelings
كائن أعزل و على ما يبدو خالياً من المشاعر
that people used to play out their darkest desires.
يستخدمه الناس لممارسة أسوء رغباتهم فيه
For more than 10 years, people who were charged with my care
لأكثر من عشرة أعوام ، أشخاص كُلفوا برعايتي
abused me physically, verbally and sexually.
أعتدوا علي جسديا ًولفظياً وجنسياً.
Despite what they thought, I did feel.
على عكس ماكانوا يعتقدون ، كنت أشعر
The first time it happened,
المرة الأولى التي حدث فيها هذا ،
I was shocked and filled with disbelief.
صُدمت وكنت غير قادراً على التصديق
How could they do this to me?
كيف يفعلون هذا بي ؟
I was confused.
كنت محتاراً،
What had I done to deserve this?
ماذا فعلت لأستحق هذا ؟
Part of me wanted to cry and another part wanted to fight.
جزء مني أراد البكاء وجزء آخر أراد القتال.
Hurt, sadness and anger flooded through me.
الأذى والحزن والغضب غمرني
I felt worthless.
شعرت بأنه لاقيمة لي .
There was no one to comfort me.
لم يكن هناك أحد ليواسيني .
But neither of my parents knew this was happening.
لاأحد من والديّ كانا على علم بما يحدث .
I lived in terror, knowing it would happen again and again.
عشت في رعب ، وأنا أعلم أنه سيحدث مرة أخرى
I just never knew when.
لكن لم أعرف متى ،
All I knew was that I would never be the same.
كل ما أعرفه باأنني لن أعود لما كنت عليه أبداً
I remember once listening to Whitney Houston singing,
أتذكر في مرة كنت أستمع إلى ويتني هيوستن تغني ،
"No matter what they take from me, they can't take away my dignity."
" لايهم مايأخذوه مني ، لكنهم لن يستطعيوا سلب كرامتي "
And I thought to myself, "You want to bet?"
وقلت لنفسي " أتريد أن تراهن " ؟
Perhaps my parents could have found out and could have helped.
لربما لو علم والديّ بالأمر لساعداني
But the years of constant caretaking,
لكن سنوات من الرعاية المتواصلة
having to wake up every two hours to turn me,
أن يستيقظا كل ساعتين ليقلباني من موضعي
combined with them essentially grieving the loss of their son,
أضافة إلى حزنهم على فقدان أبنهم ،
had taken a toll on my mother and father.
بدأ يأثر سلباً على أمي وأبي .
Following yet another heated argument between my parents,
وعقب مشادة أخرى بين والدي،
in a moment of despair and desperation,
في لحظة قنوط ويأس،
my mother turned to me and told me that I should die.
ألتفتت إلي والدتي وقالت لي يجب أن أموت
I was shocked, but as I thought about what she had said,
صُدمت ، لكن حين فكرت فيما قالته لي ،
I was filled with enormous compassion and love for my mother,
مُلئت بكم كبير من الشفقة والحب تجاه والدتي،
yet I could do nothing about it.
إلا أنه لايمكنني فعل إي شي حيال الأمر
There were many moments when I gave up,
أستسلمت في لحظات كثيرة
sinking into a dark abyss.
غرقت في هاوية مظلمة.
I remember one particularly low moment.
أتذكر لحظة بائسة بشكل خاص.
My dad left me alone in the car
والدي تركني وحيداً في السيارة
while he quickly went to buy something from the store.
في حين ذهب بسرعة لشراء شيء من المتجر.
A random stranger walked past,
غريب مر بجانبي ،
looked at me and he smiled.
نظر إلي وأبتسم.
I may never know why, but that simple act,
ربما لن أعرف أبداً ، لكن تلك الإبتسامة،
the fleeting moment of human connection,
لحظة عابرة من الاتصال البشري،
transformed how I was feeling,
غيرت كيف كنت أشعر
making me want to keep going.
جعلتني أفكر في المضي قدماً.
My existence was tortured by monotony,
وجودي كان معذباً من قبل الملل والرتابة،
a reality that was often too much to bear.
واقع في كثير من الأحيان كان صعب علي أحتماله
Alone with my thoughts, I constructed intricate fantasies
وحيداً مع أفكاري ، شيدت خيالات معقدة
about ants running across the floor.
حول النمل الذي يمر على الأرضية.
I taught myself to tell the time by noticing where the shadows were.
علمت نفسي كيف أميز الوقت عن طريق ملاحظة مكان الظل .
As I learned how the shadows moved as the hours of the day passed,
كما تعلمت كيف يتحرك الظل مع مرور ساعات النهار،
I understood how long it would be before I was picked up and taken home.
فهمت كم من الوقت سيكون قبل أن يتم أخذي للمنزل.
Seeing my father walk through the door to collect me
رؤية والدي يعبر الباب حتى يأخذني
was the best moment of the day.
كانت أجمل لحظة في اليوم.
My mind became a tool that I could use
عقلي أصبح آداة أستطيع أستخدامها
to either close down to retreat from my reality
إما للأنغلاق للأنسحاب من واقعي
or enlarge into a gigantic space that I could fill with fantasies.
أو ليكبر للفضاء الضخم الذي أستطيع ملئه بالخيال.
I hoped that my reality would change
تمنيت لو أن واقعي يتغير
and someone would see that I had come back to life.
وأن يلاحظ شخصاً ما أنني قد عُدت للحياة.
But I had been washed away like a sand castle
لكنني كنت قد جُرفت كقلعة رمل
built too close to the waves,
بُنيت بشكل قريب للأمواج،
and in my place was the person people expected me to be.
وفي مكاني كان شخص توقع مني الناس أن أكونه
To some I was Martin, a vacant shell, the vegetable,
للبعض كنت أنا مارتن ، محارة فارغة ، نبات
deserving of harsh words, dismissal and even abuse.
يستحق الكلمات القاسية والنبذ، وحتى الاعتداء.
To others, I was the tragically brain-damaged boy
للآخرين ، كنت بشكل مأساوي الولد التالف دماغياً
who had grown to become a man.
الذي كبر ليصبح رجلاً.
Someone they were kind to and cared for.
شخصاً ما كانوا قد أعتنوا فيه وعطفوا عليه.
Good or bad, I was a blank canvas
بشكل جيد أو سيء ، كنت جدارية فارغة
onto which different versions of myself were projected.
معروضة عليها نسخ مختلفة من نفسي
It took someone new to see me in a different way.
تطلب الأمر شخص جديد ليراني بشكل مختلف.
An aromatherapist began coming to the care home about once a week.
معالجة بطب الروائح بدأت في زيارة دار الرعاية مرة أسبوعياً
Whether through intuition or her attention to details
سواء عن طريق الحدس أو انتباهها للتفاصيل
that others failed to notice,
التي عجز غيرها عن ملاحظتها.
she became convinced that I could understand what was being said.
اقتنعت أنني أتمكن من فهم ما يقال.
She urged my parents to have me tested by experts
حثت والدي على عرضي وفحصي من قبل المختصين
in augmentative and alternative communication.
بالأتصال المعزز والبديل
And within a year,
وخلال عام واحد ،
I was beginning to use a computer program to communicate.
بدأت في أستخدام برنامج كمبيوتر للتواصل
It was exhilarating, but frustrating at times.
كان الأمر مبهجاً لكن محبطاً في بعض الأحيان
I had so many words in my mind,
كان لدي الكثير من الكلمات في عقلي
that I couldn't wait to be able to share them.
التي لم أكن قادراً على الأنتظار أكثر للحديث عنها.
Sometimes, I would say things to myself simply because I could.
في بعض الأحيان، أقول بعض الأمور لنفسي فقط لأني أستطيع ذلك
In myself, I had a ready audience,
داخل نفسي ، كان لدي جمهور مستعد،
and I believed that by expressing my thoughts and wishes,
واعتقدت أنه بالإعراب عن أفكاري ورغباتي،
others would listen, too.
الآخرين سيرغبون في سماعي إيضاً.
But as I began to communicate more,
لكن ما أن بدأت بالتواصل أكثر،
I realized that it was in fact only just the beginning
حتى استوعبت أنه بالواقع البداية
of creating a new voice for myself.
لخلق صوت جديد لنفسي .
I was thrust into a world I didn't quite know how to function in.
لقد أقحمت في عالم لم أعرف كيف أتعامل فيه
I stopped going to the care home
توقفت عن الذهاب لدار الرعاية
and managed to get my first job making photocopies.
وأستطعت الحصول على أول وظيفة أستخراج الصور
As simple as this may sound, it was amazing.
ببساطة كما يبدو الأمر ، كان رائعاً
My new world was really exciting
عالمي الجديد كان مثيراً
but often quite overwhelming and frightening.
ولكن في أغلب الأحيان كان مخيفاً وقاهراً
I was like a man-child,
كنت كالرجل الطفل ،
and as liberating as it often was,
على الرغم من أنه يبدو محرراً
I struggled.
عانيت.
I also learned that many of those who had known me for a long time
لقد تعلمت أيضاً ان العديد من هؤلاء الذين عرفوني لوقت طويل
found it impossible to abandon the idea of Martin they had in their heads.
وجدوا الأمر مستحيلاً أن يتخلوا عن فكرة مارتن التي علقت بأذهانهم
While those I had only just met
في حين أن أولئك الذين ألتقيت للتو
struggled to look past the image of a silent man in a wheelchair.
عانوا في رؤيتي أكثر من رجل صامت في كرسي متحرك.
I realized that some people would only listen to me
أدركت أن بعض الناس سوف يستمعون لي فقط
if what I said was in line with what they expected.
إذا كان ما قلته متماشياً مع مايتوقعون
Otherwise, it was disregarded
خلاف ذلك، يتم تجاهله
and they did what they felt was best.
ويفعلوا مايشعروا أنه الأفضل.
I discovered that true communication
اكتشفت أن التواصل الحقيقي
is about more than merely physically conveying a message.
هو أكثر من مجرد إيصال الرسالة جسدياً.
It is about getting the message heard and respected.
بل أن يتم سماعها وأحترامها
Still, things were going well.
ومع ذلك، كانت الأمور تسير على ما يرام.
My body was slowly getting stronger.
كان جسدي شيئا فشيئا أقوى.
I had a job in computing that I loved,
كانت لدي وظيفة في مجال الحوسبة التي أحببت،
and had even got Kojak, the dog I had been dreaming about for years.
وحتى حصلت على كوجاك ، الكلب الذي كنت أحلم بالحصول عليه لسنوات
However, I longed to share my life with someone.
ومع ذلك، أشتقت لمشاركة حياتي مع شخصاً ما
I remember staring out the window as my dad drove me home from work,
اتذكر كنت أحدق من النافذة حين قادني والدي عائداً من العمل،
thinking I have so much love inside of me and nobody to give it to.
أفكر بأن لدي من الحب الكثير داخلي ولايوجد شخص أبادله هذا الحب
Just as I had resigned myself to being single for the rest of my life,
في وقت ما سلمت نفسي لفكرة قضاء ماتبقى من حياتي عازباً
I met Joan.
ألتقيت (جوان)
Not only is she the best thing that has ever happened to me,
هي ليست فقط أفضل شيء حدث لي حياتي،
but Joan helped me to challenge my own misconceptions about myself.
ولكن جوان ساعدتني على تحدي مفاهيمي الخاطئة عن نفسي.
Joan said it was through my words that she fell in love with me.
قالت جوان أنها من خلال كلماتي قد وقعت في حبي
However, after all I had been through,
ومع ذلك، وبعد كل ما مررت به،
I still couldn't shake the belief
لازلت لاأستطيع تغيير الأعتقاد
that nobody could truly see beyond my disability
أنه لا أحد قد أستطاع تماماً روية ماوراء إعاقتي
and accept me for who I am.
وقبولي كما أنا .
I also really struggled to comprehend that I was a man.
وعانيت أيضاً في أدراك أنني رجل.
The first time someone referred to me as a man,
في أول مرة شخص ما أشار لي كرجل،
it stopped me in my tracks.
توقفت من المفاجأة
I felt like looking around and asking, "Who, me?"
شعرت أنني أريد النظر حولي والسؤال " من ، أنا " ؟
That all changed with Joan.
كل هذا تغير مع جوان
We have an amazing connection
لدينا علاقة مذهلة
and I learned how important it is to communicate openly and honestly.
وتعلمت كم هو مهم التواصل بصراحة وصدق.
I felt safe, and it gave me the confidence to truly say what I thought.
شعرت بالأمان، وأعطاني الثقة لقول حقاً ماظننت.
I started to feel whole again, a man worthy of love.
بدأت أشعر ككل من جديد ، رجل يستحق الحب.
I began to reshape my destiny.
بدأت أعادة تشكيل مصيري
I spoke up a little more at work.
بدأت بالتحدث أكثر في العمل
I asserted my need for independence to the people around me.
أكدت لمن حولي حاجتي للأستقلال
Being given a means of communication changed everything.
أعطائي وسيلة للاتصال غيرت كل شيء.
I used the power of words and will to challenge the preconceptions
استخدام قوة الكلمات والإرادة لتحدي مفاهيم
of those around me and those I had of myself.
هؤلاء من هم حولي ومفاهيمي أنا ايضاً
Communication is what makes us human,
التواصل هو ما يجعلنا بشر،
enabling us to connect on the deepest level
يمكننا من الإتصال على مستوى أعمق
with those around us --
بمن هم حولنا
telling our own stories,
أن نخبر قصصنا الخاصة
expressing wants, needs and desires,
التعبير عن الرغبات والاحتياجات والرغبات،
or hearing those of others by really listening.
أو سماع آراء الآخرين من خلال الاستماع حقا.
All this is how the world knows who we are.
كل هذا هو من يعرف العالم من نحن.
So who are we without it?
لذا من نحن بدونه ؟
True communication increases understanding
التواصل الحقيقي يرفع من الفهم
and creates a more caring and compassionate world.
ويخلق عالم أكثر عطف ورحمة.
Once, I was perceived to be an inanimate object,
في مرة كان ينظر لي ككائن جماد
a mindless phantom of a boy in a wheelchair.
شبح أبله لصبي في كرسي متحرك.
Today, I am so much more.
واليوم ، أنا أكثر بكثير من هذا
A husband, a son, a friend,
زوج ، إبن ، صديق،
a brother, a business owner, a first-class honors graduate,
أخ، صاحب عمل، خريج مع مرتبة الشرف الأولى،
a keen amateur photographer.
مصور هاو ومتحمس.
It is my ability to communicate that has given me all this.
قدرتي على التواصل مكنتني من هذا كله
We are told that actions speak louder than words.
قيل لنا أن الأفعال أعلى صوتا من الأقوال.
But I wonder,
ولكن أتساءل،
do they?
هل هذا فعلاً ؟
Our words, however we communicate them,
كلماتنا ، كيفما تواصلنا بها
are just as powerful.
قوية تماماً
Whether we speak the words with our own voices,
سواء قلنا الكلمات بأصواتنا ،
type them with our eyes,
أو كتبناها بأعيننا،
or communicate them non-verbally to someone who speaks them for us,
أو تواصلنا بها بطريقة غير لفظية لشخص ينقلها بالنيابة عنا
words are among our most powerful tools.
الكلمات من أقوى أدواتنا.
I have come to you through a terrible darkness,
لقد جئت إليكم من خلال الظلام الرهيب
pulled from it by caring souls
سحبت منه بمساعدة نفوس طيبة
and by language itself.
وعن طريق اللغة نفسها.
The act of you listening to me today brings me farther into the light.
أستماعكم إلي اليوم يشدني قدماً إلى النور.
We are shining here together.
نحن نسطع هنا سويةً
If there is one most difficult obstacle to my way of communicating,
أصعب عقبة تواجهني في طريقتي في التواصل
it is that sometimes I want to shout
هي أنني في بعض الأحيان أود الصراخ
and other times simply to whisper a word of love or gratitude.
وبعض الأحيان ببساطة أن أهمس كلمة حب أو أمتنان.
It all sounds the same.
كلها تبدو متشابهه.
But if you will,
لكن لو سمحتم ،
please imagine these next two words as warmly as you can:
أرجوكم تخيلوا الكلمات المقبلة بحرارة قدر ماأستطعتم :
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)